Guide to the Marjorie Henderson and Ruth Plumly Thompson archive M2024
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Marjorie Henderson and Ruth Plumly Thompson archive
circa 1915-1940
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Thompson, Ruth Plumly, 1893-1976
Marge, 1904-1993
M2024
2 Linear Feet 3 flat boxes, 1 manuscript box, 1 small map folder
The archive consists largely of Marjorie Henderson's drawings and illustrated letters to her friend and collaborator, Ruth Plumly Thompson. Also included are photographs, ink drawings, and approximately 300 tear sheets of a cartoon "Forgetiquette" on which they collaborated.
Biography
Marjorie Henderson (popularly known as Marge) was a talented cartoonist, who by 19 years of age, was already a regular contributor to the Saturday Evening Post among other publications. She grew up on the Main Line of Philadelphia. When she was eleven years old, she began a correspondence with the editor of the children's page at the Philadelphia Public Ledger, another writer, Ruth Plumly Thompson. They began a life long friendship and collaboration.
Related Materials
Marge Papers, 1856-1994 (MC 554). Schlesinger Library, Radcliffe Institute, Harvard University, Cambridge, Mass.
Scope and Contents
The archive consists largely of Marjorie Henderson's drawings and illustrated letters to her friend and collaborator, Ruth Plumly Thompson. Included are photographs, ink drawings - some with watercolor, pen and ink margettes for a daily newspaper with verses by Ruth Thompson, and approximately 300 printed daily tear sheets of a cartoon "Forgetiquette" on which they collaborated. Her letters document daily life and events on the Main Line in Philadelphia, family vacations, local gossip, collaborative projects, and eventually marriage and children.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research use.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was purchased by Stanford University Libraries in 2014.
Artists as authors -- United States; Caricatures and cartoons -- United States; Women cartoonists -- United States; Comic books, strips, etc.; Thompson, Ruth Plumly, 1893-1976; Marge, 1904-1993
- Photographs of Marge, 1920s-1930s (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Cartoon: The Parade of the Younger Generation (printed) (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Booklet, 1916, entitled: My Brownbrook Quartette Book" (pencil sketches, pen and ink with watercolor) (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Greeting cards (pen and ink with watercolors), undated (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
- Pen and ink drawings by Marge (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Letter from Stuart Rose, editor of Little, Brown, & Co., to Marge, 1933 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Envelopes (empty), from Marge to Thompson, 1929-1934 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Ruth Thompson, "Didja Evers" (typescripts) (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Thompson's letters to various editors, 1920-1927; includes essays about Marge by Ruth Thompson. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Forgetiquette mock ups (pen and ink) (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Forgetiquette tear sheets (printed), 1924 (Box 1, Folder 12-15)
- Drawings by Marge (pen and ink) (Flat-boxes 2, Folder 1)
- Drawings by Marge (pen and ink with watercolor) (Flat-boxes 2, Folder 2)
- Fairy princess and elf subjects, circa 1917 (pen and ink with watercolor) (Flat-boxes 2, Folder 3-5)
- Letters from Marge to Ruth Thompson, most undated (handwritten with pen and ink drawings, with watercolor) (Flat-boxes 3, Folder 1-9)
- Letters from Marge to Ruth Thompson, most undated (handwritten with pen and ink drawings, and watercolors) (Flat-boxes 4, Folder 1-10)
- Booklet by Marge after visit with Ruth Thompson in Stone Harbor (pen and ink with watercolor) (Flat-boxes 3, Folder 10)
- Spreads from the Ledger Syndicate (Philadelphia, Pennsylvania), circa 1920s: "The Boy Friend" (2) and "Steaming Youth" (1), both by Marjorie Henderson (Map-folder 5)